Yes, it is actually confirmed.
是的  已經確認過了
1.6 million dollar prize pool!
總獎金一百六十萬美金
I'm double-checking to make sure they haven't changed any details
我正在反覆確認各方面細節
since they told us last time.
是否跟上一次所說的不同
1 million in US dollars for First Prize.
第一名獎金真的是100萬美元
That is for the winner.
這是為冠軍提供的
1 million dollars for winning Dota!
贏得Dota比賽的勝利就能獲得100萬美金
It's going to be huge.
這一定會風靡全球
Dota2.com, the tournament tab is up, too.
官網連比賽的標籤都有了
Our website will actually change for the next 24 hours as well...
同樣我們的網站也會在接下來的24小時裡跟進報導…
The day I transformed into an adult was the day I started playing Dota.
成為職業Dota選手就是我的成人禮
It's times like, when you go up on the stage,
有些時候  比如在你走上賽場時
you represent your country for something.
你就代表了你的國家
You get the prize.
你獲得了名次
It's the amount of satisfaction and achievement that nothing else can give you.
這種滿足感和成就感是無可比擬的
It's something I definitely don't regret ever doing.
我肯定不會後悔選擇了這條路
Gaming is simply the proudest thing in my life.
進入競技圈是我一生中最值得驕傲的事情
It can be called "gamer", but for me, it's something different.
你可以叫我“玩家”  不過這對我來說有著特殊的意義
One way to forget about pain is to do something that you will be in completely.
忘記痛苦的一種方式就是去做一件你會全情投入的事情
So, computer games.
所以  我選擇了電腦遊戲
For me, it was everything.
對我來說  它是我的一切
This is my career I've chosen to do it for so long.
這是我自己選擇一直走到現在的路
Success in my eyes is always based on how other people see you.
在我看來  成功只是取決於他人對你的評價
In the eyes of the public,
至於其他人如何定義成功
it's up to them.
就隨他們吧
It's important to be doing things that you love and you really appreciate.
做自己所欣賞並熱愛的事情是非常重要的
Because that's your passion, man.
因為那是熱情的所在
You should really work for your passions.
人總得為夢想活一次
Ok, guys, you have 7 minutes to set everything up
好的各位  你們有7分鐘的時間做好準備
and then we go.
然後我們就開始
This is the first time I really wanted to take something seriously,
這是我第一次如此認真的對待一件事
and do something good for my life.
也是我這一輩子第一次為自己去做對的事
本字幕由 今晚月色真美 製作
僅供練習使用  請勿用於商業用途
特別說明
本字幕以官方簡體中文字幕為基礎製作
本人只是修改了其中比賽解說部分的翻譯
讓其更貼近刀塔玩家的用語習慣
其他絕大部分翻譯未做修改
此外還對全片的時間軸進行了調整
原譯者如下：
陳銘胤（Hippo）
李淮（Robin）
趙曉路（zedraxlo）
孫天澤（ReShine）
孟凌（Merlin）
Bobby Liu（Bob）
向各位譯者表達最誠摯的感謝！
10 years ago, competitive gaming wasn't even really a thing.
十年以前  基本都沒有電子競技的概念
You would play for fun against your friends.
你和你的朋友對戰只是為了娛樂
Maybe you would play for a cup of coffee or whatever you wanted.
也許你們會賭一杯咖啡什麼的
When I started playing, we'd been fighting for 24 bottles of beer as a first place.
我最開始玩的時候  我們規定第一名能夠贏得24瓶啤酒
I'm not joking.
我沒開玩笑
From there, though, online happened.
不過就是從那時候起  線上賽就開始了
And, all of a sudden, you weren't just trying to be the best on your block.
接下來  你突然就不滿足於只是小區裡的第一名了
Now you're trying to be the best in the world.
現在你正為了成為世界冠軍而奮鬥
And that opened up competitive gaming to a whole new landscape.
這種精神為電子競技開啟了一個新的篇章
And one of the games really leading the way is Dota.
在這一篇章中  Dota無疑是最為濃墨重彩的一筆
Dota is sort of a combination of football or soccer for the Americans and Chess.
Dota就好像是足球的拚搏加上了象棋的睿智
This is probably how I would try to explain Dota to someone who's not familiar with it.
如果要讓我對不了解Dota的人解釋  我就會這麼說
At least, that's what I did to my parents.
反正我對我父母就是這麼解釋的
Dota is a game of momentum.
Dota是一個攸關氣勢的遊戲
You as 5 players,
你和另外4名玩家
try and battle against the other 5 players for momentum.
和對面的5名玩家對抗來獲得氣勢
Every single player controls one unit.
每個玩家控制一個單位
And the main objective of the game is to destroy the final enemy building,
遊戲目標就是摧毀敵方的終極建築
which is called the "Ancient".
這個建築被稱為“遺跡”
Everything else that happens in the meantime,
而在這一建築被摧毀前發生的所有遊戲過程
is your amazing filler of a game.
正是這個遊戲不可思議的地方
You could play 100 heroes,
有100個英雄供你選擇使用
in conjunction with 99 other heroes.
而當你面對剩下的99個英雄時  發生的事情也會不同
It's just nonstop possibilities and it's so much fun.
這遊戲有著無窮的可能性  所以玩起來其樂無窮
And you know, it's like the same map every single time,
而且你看  每次都是同一張地圖
but it literally never gets boring.
但這遊戲永遠不會讓你覺得無趣
I would say Dota is a way of life.
我覺得Dota是一種生活方式
When the prizes started coming,
當有人設立獎金時
I was like, well we have tournaments,
我的想法就是  哦我們有比賽了
so obviously some people are going to come and say,
很自然的就會有人過來說
"This is a great game. Let's play it. Like, let's put money in it."
“這是個偉大的遊戲  我們一起參與吧  意思就是  我們投資吧”
And it started progressing each year.
而且投資一年比一年多
Those at the top level,
那些頂級的選手
they just do like lots of calculations in their head.
他們的腦中會進行很多運算
Something like "A Beautiful Mind".
有點像《美麗心靈》裡的天才
where you see like all kinds of things.
這些人能夠預見到各種可能
And using all this information make your next move.
並且基於他們所獲取這些的資訊來做出下一步動作
I see it in a lot of ways similar to basketball.
這和籃球在很多地方都有相似之處
Just like a 5 on 5 game.
都是5V5的比賽
where you kind of have to work together,
大家都得齊心協力
and utilize each other's strengths and synergizing everything together.
充分利用每個人的特長並且彼此磨合  產生默契
The teamwork, and the trust, and the sacrifice,
團隊配合  信任和犧牲
those are all true for every single team sport.
每項團體運動都有這些東西
Dota is a game that unites everybody.
Dota這個遊戲將所有人團結起來
It doesn't matter what country you're from or race you are.
你的國籍和種族並不重要
It's kind of like a bond that is shared,
這就像是一種連接彼此的紐帶
and when you're part of this tight-knit group of people.
當你成為這個緊密團體的一員時
It's like having a second family.
他們就成了你的家人
That's something you never let go.
這種感情你永遠不會放手
Everyone's searching for something.
每個人都在追尋著一些東西
Fulfillment.
自我實現
Fame.
名譽
Satisfaction.
自我滿足
It gives you the ability to become someone else.
它讓你成為一個不同的人
A someone who is powerful.
一個強大的人
Who can take down 5 opponents.
一個能夠解決5個對手的人
Express their creativity.
展現選手自身的創造力
Break the rules without actually getting arrested.
可以不守規矩  還不用擔心受罰
All of these reasons are in there somewhere.
這一切都在這個遊戲裡
The player himself might not even know.
玩家自身可能都不會意識到
He might not even understand it himself.
甚至可能都無法理解
But it's there.
但遊戲的內涵就是如此
Gaming fulfills my competitive need.
遊戲滿足了我對競技的渴望
I'm a very competitive person.
我是一個好勝心很強的人
When it comes to sports, I consider gaming a sport.
說到體育運動  我覺得遊戲也是一種運動
So I use my competitiveness and I fuel it with Dota.
於是我充分發揮自己的好勝心  而Dota點燃了我的激情
So it fulfills that side of me completely.
所以它完全滿足了我的競技需求
Fear's one of the best in America, if not the best.
Fear是美國最優秀的選手  先加上“之一”吧
He has a lot of experience.
他經驗老道
He's one of the old hogs, basically.
基本算是最老的一批選手了
And he's generally just a calm guy.
他通常十分冷靜
So, in my opinion, that's his strength.
所以在我看來  冷靜就是他的力量
Really good basketball player, I remember.
打籃球真的有一手
My coaches watch him playing,
我還記得我的教練看他打球
and just talk about picking him up the next year when he came in.
就說明年他來的時候要把他招過來
Always had nothing but good things to say,
一談起他總是溢美之詞不斷
but he wasn't picked on the team.
不過他後來沒有入選籃球隊
Just the reason was, yeah, he just wasn't tall enough, I guess.
理由的話  我覺得是他還不夠高吧
So, I know that, yeah, he found the game, I really devoted in that stuff.
後來嘛  沒錯  我知道  他後來發現了這個遊戲  他完全投入其中
and just found something else that worked.
然後發現了另外一件能做的事
I was your typical parent.
我是那種很典型的家長
"Clinton, you're spending too much time playing computer games."
我總是說  “Clinton  你玩遊戲的時間太長了”
"You need to go to school."
“你該去上學了”
"You need to go to college."
“你得上大學啊”
and he would tell me,
然後他就會說
"I want to be able to play games and get paid for it."
“我想有人給我發工資讓我玩遊戲”
Now he said this at a very young age,
他很小的時候就說了這句話
before Dota ever came along.
當時還沒有Dota
And I thought, well, you know, he's going to grow out of it.
我就想  好吧  他總會長大的
He's going to get sick and tired of sitting there in front of that computer and playing.
一直坐在那裡玩遊戲  總有一天他會覺得沒意思的
Never did. Never did.
結果他根本沒有  從來沒有
In Singapore, the families actually put a lot of stress on us in terms of our education.
在新加坡  家人給我們的壓力很大  主要是在教育方面
I would say it's been tough on me trying to juggle both studies and gaming at the same time.
對我來說  同時兼顧我的學業和職業生涯從來都不是一件簡單的事情
My grades have dropped for two years already.
連續兩年我的學習成績都在下滑
And my parents have treated the gaming as the cause of it.
我的父母認為是遊戲導致的
I mean there was this phrase that they used.
他們以前常說一句話
They said, "Gaming will be the death of you one day."
“總有一天遊戲會害死你的”
He's a great player and a great captain.
他是一個偉大的選手  一個偉大的隊長
I would say he's the top player in Singapore.
在我看來他是新加坡最頂尖的選手
Easily.
毫無疑問
My parents and my family, they don't actually speak much of my gaming career.
我的父母和家人對我的職業生涯並沒有說太多
They don't tell their friends and my other relatives,
他們沒有告訴他們的親戚朋友
that I'm actually that good at my games.
其實我玩遊戲很厲害
All along they have only been bragging about my studies.
他們一直都是對外人說我學習很好
Because I used to be an "A" student.
因為我以前是“資優生”
Yeah, they go on and on, and…
他們一直對別人這麼說啊說  而且…
And it seemed like that was the only thing they could ever be proud of.
而且這好像是他們唯一值得驕傲的事情
Actually, there has only been one person,
其實  一直以來只有一個人
that has always been very supportive of me gaming.
從始至終支持我的職業電競生涯
And that was my ex-girlfriend, Huayan.
就是我的前女友  華燕
She's from the female Dota team in Singapore.
她是新加坡女子Dota戰隊的成員
There are a lot of things that we share in life.
我們在生活中有很多共同之處
So many things.
很多很多
In my case, it felt really good, you know, to have someone who truly appreciated what you did best.
對我來說  這種感覺真的很好  就是有一個人發自內心的欣賞我最擅長的事情
And loved you for it.
並且因此愛上我
She was aware of what I'm doing and what I'm passionate about.
她很明白我做的事情  很明白我的熱情所在
The breakup was her decision and I respected it.
分手是她提的  我尊重她的選擇
We'd been together for close to three years,
我們在一起快三年
and ever since the breakup, I haven't gotten over it.
我到現在還沒有走出分手的陰影
I recall the last time she spoke to me,
我還記得她最後一次跟我說話
She named me as a bastard so…
她說我是個混蛋…
We're not in contact anymore, yeah, but…
我們不再聯繫了  但是…
life goes on.
生活還是要繼續
I'm from Ukraine.
我來自烏克蘭
My nickname is Dendi.
我的暱稱是Dendi
I finished my university, and…
我讀完了大學以後
I'm just playing computer games right now.
成為了一名職業遊戲選手  一直到現在
Он занимался музыкой.
他以前學音樂
Он играл на фортепиано.
練過鋼琴
Он занимался танцами.
他以前還跳舞
В школе мы ставили музыкальные сказки, где он исполнял главные роли.
在學校裡  他還出演過音樂劇的主角
Зрители всегда восхищались его артистичностью.
觀眾們都被他的藝術天賦所征服
Их детская группа выступала, Данила очень выделялся.
當一幫孩子聚在一起時  丹尼爾總是最出眾的那個
When we were growing up
在我們小時候
it wasn't a good time financially for our family.
家裡的經濟條件並不是很好
But my grandma helped us to get our first computer in 1997.
不過我們的奶奶還是在1997年為我們買了我們的第一台電腦
Early, compared with other kids in Ukraine.
所以  和烏克蘭的其他孩子不一樣的是
We got visitors every day.
每天都有人到我們家裡來玩
The friends of my older brother used to come to visit us,
我哥哥的朋友以前也總來串門
and we were playing games.
我們一起玩遊戲
And Danil, every time looked at what we do.
丹尼爾每次都會來看我們玩
Every time we would try to push him away,
每次我們都讓他閃開
but he would come back and look again.
但是這小孩黏人得很
Это было всё в большей степени, чем у моих детей.
他小時候對電腦的興趣比其他小孩都要強烈
During all his conscious life,
從他記事開始
we were trying to stop him from playing.
我們就一直在想方設法讓他不玩遊戲
We were hiding our computer cord everywhere in our apartment,
我們把電腦線藏起來  家裡到處都藏過了
but he always found it.
但他總是能找到
Мне всегда хотелось его больше понять.
我總是想多了解他一點
Даже его вот то увлечение мне хотелось больше понять, и…
包括遊戲這一愛好  我一直想去更了解他…
Ну, были на то причины.
其中有某些原因
Я не буду о них сейчас говорить.
我現在不想再提了
Ну, думаю, где-то в душе он, наверное, немножко жалеет, что он.
我認為在他內心深處  他總是有一些悲傷
She stopped preventing him from playing Dota.
她後來就不攔著他玩Dota
She gave Dendi the freedom to choose,
她給了Dendi選擇的自由
what is the best for him and his life.
讓他選擇自己覺得最好的
Tournaments back then were really low prizes.
當時的比賽獎金普遍很低
And a lot of prize money didn't even get to the players.
甚至很多比賽獎金都發不到選手手上
There's been a lot of scams with the managers and stuff like that.
經理們總是做一些坑人的事
There were, like, some rumors that it's going to be $50,000 first place,
比如  賽事的報導聲稱冠軍能拿到5萬美金
and everyone was going, like, "Nah, it's not going to be like that."
然後每個人都覺得  “噗  怎麼可能”
Watch the forums go nuts, guys.
大家快來看  整個論壇都瘋了
Watch the forums go nuts.
整個論壇都瘋了
It is actually confirmed.
已經確定了
It is off the fricking hook.
消息都正式宣布了
1.6 million dollar prize pool!
總獎金160萬美金
That is for the winner,
而贏得本屆Dota比賽的冠軍
1 million dollars for winning Dota!
將拿到100萬美金
Dota, the game I've played for 5 years now.
Dota  我玩了5年的遊戲
Which I played for fun.
我用來娛樂的遊戲
For some food money or whatever, you know.
本來玩這個也就是掙點便當錢
Ok, it's actually getting big.
好吧  它開始火了
It's the largest prize pool of any gaming competition to date.
這是迄今為止電子競技比賽歷史上最高的獎金
It just felt like the start of something big.
但這感覺僅僅是一個開始
Like a revolution.
就像一場革命
You know, we had everything we needed,
為了讓這個遊戲規模變大  讓電子競技受人尊重
for the game to become big and respected as an E-sport.
我們準備得很充分
It would kind of like vindicate us.
這有點像可以證明我們的價值
We're not just playing because we're addicted.
我們並不是因為上癮了才玩遊戲
There's a goal, a motive.
我們有了動力  有了目標
That we can actually reach out and grab if we are good enough.
一個只要我們足夠優秀  我們總能達到的目標
Over in Asia, professional gamers are treated like rock stars.
在整個亞洲  職業玩家的待遇和搖滾明星差不多
It's a viable career opportunity.
成為職業選手是一條可行的道路
They actually live in gamer houses.
會有專門的選手基地讓他們住
So it's set up to be a thing all year long.
沒錯  的確會建這樣一座選手基地
I think their approach to practice is that it's like a day job.
我覺得訓練就是他們的日常工作
The fan base is immense.
中國的粉絲基礎非常龐大
It probably is as big as the whole western audience together.
人數可能和整個西方社會的遊戲用戶一樣多
Or even more than that.
甚至更多
So now you really have to play good.
所以你必須非常厲害
You really have to try hard.
你必須刻苦訓練
It's first place. It's go big or go home.
贏是你的第一要務  要嘛贏  要嘛回家
The big teams get big money.
名次靠前的隊伍才能獲得獎金
But the 9th to 16th place earn nothing.
然而9到16名什麼都沒有
And their salaries are not worth considering.
他們的工資不值一提
While in sports, you have a salary that you can live on.
在體育界  你至少有一份能維持生計的工資
With pro gaming, I think that's one of the toughest parts is
而在職業電競行業  我認為最難的一點就是
living game to game.
需要靠一場接一場的比賽才能活下去
It's like living paycheck to paycheck.
就像完全靠工資存活一樣
Like, I have to win. If I don't win, I don't get paid.
打個比方就是  我必須贏  如果我輸了  那就沒工資了
That's a tough living for anybody. It doesn't matter what you're doing.
這種生活對任何人來說都很難  和你現在所做的事情無關
When your child wants to be a professional gamer,
當你的孩子想成為一名職業玩家時
you don't have any history to look back on,
你發現並沒有這方面的經驗可以借鑑
like other sports.
這和其他體育運動不一樣
I don't know anyone who's made a living at gaming.
我認識的人裡沒有靠玩遊戲來養家餬口的
So it's kind of a scary thing,
所以當你發現自己的孩子將整個生活都投入到遊戲中
when you see your kid putting their whole life into gaming,
而不是上大學或者其他傳統行業時
and not college and not the traditional things.
你會覺得心裡非常沒底
What if nothing comes of it?
要是打不出成績怎麼辦？
Regarding the age,
對於選手年齡方面
I think, yes,
我認為  嗯
25, 26 years. It's absolutely maximum for E-sports,
25  26歲已經是電競選手的極限了
Because 27, 28, 29, 30,
因為過了26歲以後
your reaction time is lowering,
你的臨場反應時間就會變長
and you can't click so much, you know,
和小孩子比起來
as the kids do.
你點滑鼠也會變慢
A lot of financial responsibilities are laid upon me right now.
我現在肩負著很多經濟方面的責任
Require me to be successful in something or have a job.
這就要求我必須在某些事情上成功  或者找個工作
So it's pretty critical that I am successful if I want to continue the gaming career.
所以如果我想繼續我的職業生涯  我就必須成功
He's an "A-Star" student, you know?
他是一個優等生  你知道嗎？
Because of this gaming, it pulled him right down.
但因為遊戲  他墮落了
It's very sad for me.
這讓我很難受
So here the bad one is Auntie.
我這個阿姨總是當壞人的
Auntie is the one that always comes here and nag, nag, nag, nag, nag.
我總是走到他邊上不停的嘮叨
Am I right?
我說的沒錯吧？
It's tough being a gamer.
當一名職業電競選手很難
Sorry? Am I right?
什麼？我說的沒錯吧？
I said, it's tough being a gamer.
我說要做一名職業電競選手很難
Huh, hy? Multi-millionaire.
蛤  百萬富翁hy？
For gaming, huh?
遊戲界的百萬富翁  是吧？
Sorry, you are not.
對不起  你不是
Huh? What is your view? What is your plan?
嗯？你的眼界呢？你的計劃呢？
That is more important.
那些才是更重要的東西
I mean, we speak ourselves.
我是說  這是我們的想法
We speak our frank opinion.
這是我們最直接的想法
This is your choice now.
到你做出選擇的時候了
What do you want in life? That is more important.
你這輩子想要什麼  這才是最重要的
If I'm going to win this tournament,
如果我想贏得這次比賽
my first thought would be…
我的第一個念頭會是…
I will call my ex-girlfriend.
打電話給我的前女友
Things got real bad between us and…
我們之前弄得很不愉快…
but right now, for me, if I'm going to win this tournament,
不過現在對我來說  如果我贏下這次比賽
my first thought would be, yeah, I would call her.
我的第一個念頭會是  嗯  給她打電話
I would tell her about it and…
我會告訴她我贏了…
I would want to share this moment with her…
我想和她分享那一刻…
Yeah.
就是這樣
This tournament is going to be a moment in every gamer's life.
這次比賽對每個選手來說都是生命中難忘的一刻
Everything that you've been doing has been building up,
你所有的訓練  所做的事情
and is going to happen over one week.
都將在這一週內受到檢驗
And then it's not one week anymore.
接下來甚至不是一週
It's one game.
而是一場比賽
And then it's not that one game.
然後也不是那一場比賽
it's that one moment in the game.
而是比賽中的某個時刻
And then that one moment in the game is where it's going to finish.
那一刻將會是你的謝幕演出
And how's it going to finish?
然而謝幕的方式是怎樣呢？
Are you going to be holding up a trophy?
你會手捧獎盃謝幕嗎？
Or are you going to be the most disappointed that you've ever been?
還是這一刻將成為你生命中最大的遺憾？
It's Tuesday.
今天是星期二
So one day before the event.
離比賽開始還有一天
We already have a lot of setup.
我們已經準備了很多
We have a lot of computer setup right here.
我們在這裡準備了很多電腦
The whole booth construction pretty much finished.
整個選手間的搭建也基本完成了
So five players per side.
每一邊有五名選手
They can see each other through the glass.
他們可以透過玻璃看到彼此
They can't hear each other.
但他們聽不到對方說話
This booth is soundproofed up.
整個選手間都是隔音的
Plus, the whole setup here,
另外  整個比賽場地的搭建
if you look from above looks exactly like a Dota map.
如果你從上面俯視  它看起來就和Dota地圖一樣
And this is the mid.
這是中路
This is where it all happens.
這就是比賽進行的地方
A few teams have already arrived this morning.
不少隊伍在今早已經到了
We had a lot of teams from Singapore.
我們有很多從新加坡來的隊伍
We have China.
還有中國的隊伍
We had Malaysia coming in,
馬來西亞的隊伍
and Russia.
以及俄羅斯的隊伍
And tomorrow it's finally happening.
明天大賽終於要開始了
We're here live at Gamescom 2011 in beautiful Cologne.
這裡是2011年科隆遊戲展的現場直播
It's the first day of the event.
這是第一個比賽日
We've got some of the world's best teams here in Dota.
這裡有全世界最頂尖的Dota隊伍
And they're handing out a tournament prize of 1.6 million dollars!
主辦方將會發出一百六十萬美元的獎金
It is massive here.
這裡盛況空前
A tournament of 1.6 million dollars.
一個一百六十萬美金的比賽
That's the future of gaming.
這是電子競技的未來
This is awesome!
這真是太棒了
It's the first time we're going to see teams of this caliber assembled in one location.
這是我們第一次看到如此水準的隊伍匯集一堂
These guys are not just nameless faces.
這些人並不是無名之輩
They're the best in the world.
他們是全世界選手中的精英
The bunch of teams we have here,
在我們邀請到的隊伍中
there's a few teams that have individual skill that's unbelievable.
有的隊伍的選手有著難以置信的個人能力
And then there's a big group of other teams,
而另外一部分隊伍
that have good individual skill, not top-notch,
他們隊員的個人水平同樣出色  也許不是最好的
but who win through good strategy and team play.
但是他們的戰術和團隊執行力是勝利的保證
Fear is a great player, for example,
比如說  Fear是名非常優秀的選手
but he is not comparable to good players in Asia.
但是他與亞洲的頂級選手並不能相提並論
And that's nothing against Fear, because he's still an excellent player,
不是說Fear不好  因為他的實力的確超群
but he's not them.
但他個人技術還是不如亞洲選手
Over in Asia, they take gaming so much more seriously.
在亞洲  選手們對待比賽的態度更為嚴肅
Just to give you an example,
我給你舉這麼個例子吧
the Korean soccer team were playing in the World Cup.
在世界盃上的韓國足球運動員
To motivate the Korean soccer team to play better,
他們在更衣室準備比賽的時候
they brought in Starcraft Brood War professional gamers
會安排與他們心中的英雄
into their locker room before they went out,
《星海爭霸》的職業選手相見
so that they got to meet what were their heroes.
以此來激發他們的士氣
In China, Dota is to the people there what Starcraft is to Korea.
在中國  Dota對人們的意義就像《星海爭霸》對韓國人的意義一樣
Um, it's televised.
電視台會直播比賽
The girls like their boyfriends to be Dota players.
女生們都想她們的男朋友成為Dota職業選手
After a game, when they're walking around,
比賽結束以後    當他們離開時
you can see fans running up to them,
粉絲們都會向著他們衝過去
asking them to sign on their shirts.
請他們在自己的衣服上簽名
It's like a real sport.
這就和傳統體育一樣
The third time I was in China, I was playing with fans for two days.
我第三次去中國的時候  我和粉絲們一起玩了兩天
They made a video of me,
他們為我做了個影片
filming me walking in some mountains and I had to say some sentences and stuff.
拍下了我去登山的情景  我還得對著鏡頭說話
And I was like, yeah, "In Dota, there's always a new mountain to climb."
我當時說的是“在Dota界  你總是需要翻越不同的大山”
Stuff like this, you know. And…
大概說的是這個吧…
I walked up and down these stairs
我來回的爬著階梯
and started running and lifting some weights,
還跑了步  舉了重
just to compare this with Dota like some metaphor and stuff.
就是為了將Dota比喻成這些運動
E-sports in China is already a sport,
電子競技它在中國
that is recognized by the General Administration of Sport.
它就是一個被國家體育總局承認的體育項目
It is the same as tennis, ping pong, chess.
和羽毛球  桌球  象棋一樣
The only thing is that it is not an Olympic sport.
只不過它是一個非奧項目
I will say that China teams are all great.
中國隊伍都很厲害
Every player in the team is strong.
每個選手都很強
You don't recognize China players as a player.
中國選手並不是因個人而受到認可
You just recognize them as a whole team.
而是他們組成的戰隊被人們所認可
You just fear the whole team.
你會對這樣的隊伍心生寒意
The Chinese teams that have come to this competition are scaring the shit out of everyone else.
來到這次比賽的中國隊伍把其他人直接嚇出了翔
We had two of the top Chinese teams in our group.
我們的組裡有兩支中國的頂級隊伍
Online Kingdom has not been regarded as one of the favorites to win it.
一直以來人們對Online Kingdom的實力就不太肯定
In fact, they were considered bottom four or just bottom eight for sure.
事實上  大家都認為他們是倒數四名  反正肯定排不進前八
This is our first time on LAN together.
這是我們第一次參加線下比賽
The team together has only been around for around 4-5 months
這支隊伍在四五個月前才集合完畢
so it's a relatively new team,
因此他們算是一支很新的隊伍
and Pajkatt, our newest addition, playing Carry for us,
而Pajkatt是最新加入的隊員  是隊裡的一號位
he's only been on the team for three weeks now actually.
事實上他加入戰隊才三個星期
We were really nervous going against a Chinese team,
和中國隊伍打  我們非常緊張
especially the top Chinese teams.
尤其是頂級的中國隊伍
There are going to be players that choke handling this kind of pressure at such a young age.
這些如此年輕的選手在面對如此壓力時  難免會有人發揮失常
1437, this is the first time he's ever been on LAN.
而1437這名選手也是第一次參加線下比賽
It's not easy, like, this is a million dollar tournament.
這可不是個小比賽  這可是百萬美金大賽
First time he's been on LAN.
第一次線下賽  經驗等於是0
This stage. This prize money. This prestige.
這種大場合  如此高的獎金和出名機會
This is real competition.
這是真正意義上的比賽
We tried to keep our cool together,
我們努力讓自己保持冷靜
and we just played our game.
發揮正常水準就可以了
We were super hyped.
所有人都在討論我們
Everyone was surprised we were doing so good.
我們的表現驚艷全場
Even we couldn't believe it.
我們自己都覺得難以置信
Online Kingdom dominating right now.
Online Kingdom正在主宰比賽
After the match against TyLoo, everyone was very excited, you know.
對天祿的比賽結束以後，大家都很興奮
We just beat one of the teams that was actually favored to win the competition.
我們剛擊敗的隊伍可是奪冠熱門
So everyone's spirits were, like…
大家都士氣高漲  就像…
"Oh, we may be actually able to do this, you know."
“哦  我們可能真的能拿冠軍”
Beating the Chinese teams,
擊敗了中國隊伍以後
some people just, you know for fun, they started,
有的人就開始開玩笑說
"Ok, hey, it's OK.Nirvana.Int. They're the China slayers."
“看啊  是Online Kingdom  他們是中國隊剋星。”
A few little bit surprises that we had yesterday.
昨天發生了不少出人意料的事
Quite a few upsets.
好幾個比賽都爆冷
OK.Nirvana.International managing to beat two Chinese teams in a row,
Online Kingdom連續擊敗了兩支中國隊伍
beating out TyLoo and OK.Nirvana.CN.
擊敗了Tyloo和Nirvana.CN
They're currently on a roll now.
他們現在勢頭不錯
And Chinese teams are not unbeatable.
中國隊伍也不是不可戰勝的嘛
But on the other hand,
不過另一方面
EHOME are just proving that they are the strongest of the four Chinese teams
EHOME證明了他們是四支中國隊伍裡最強的
having a clean 3-0 record.
乾淨俐落的3-0的戰績
They are the favorites to win the whole tournament.
他們是奪冠呼聲最高的隊伍
So they come in with the confidence,
因此他們信心滿滿
that they've won so many championships already.
特別是他們已經贏得了無數的冠軍
It's always a little bit of national pride at stake.
這裡面總有一些國家榮譽感
So, of course, they want to prove that Chinese Dota is still a little bit above the rest.
所以  他們當然想證明中國Dota還是領先世界的
EHOME is one of the oldest Chinese Dota organizations.
EHOME是中國Dota的老牌俱樂部之一
They've always been at the top of competitive gaming.
他們一直是電子競技的豪門戰隊
Most memorably at ESWC 2010.
尤其是在2010年電子競技世界盃上
Before ESWC 2010,
在那次比賽之前
I thought, like, yeah ok, the Chinese, they're probably pretty good,
我的想法是  好吧  中國隊伍  他們可能還行吧
but like how good can they be?
但是到底有多厲害
And then we played EHOME who won that tournament without losing a single match.
然後我們當時就和後來的冠軍EHOME進行了比賽  整個ESWC他們未嘗一敗
Like, they just crushed every team.
他們就那樣碾壓了所有隊伍
EHOME finished the year as the best team in the history of Dota.
EHOME帶著Dota歷史上最輝煌的成績結束了那一年
They were just like on a totally different level.
他們的水準比其他人高出太多
Like, they had their manager sitting behind them.
比如說  他們的經理就坐在他們後面
He was making their calls.
是他在做各種決策
He was running around with this little black book.
他還一直隨身帶著他的小黑本
And they were the first team I heard of who did that.
我頭一回聽說有隊伍如此專業
The EHOME manager copying down the draft, doing the prep work.
EHOME的經理記下了選人  做了準備工作
He was their coach.
他就相當於隊員們的教練
There was a great interview that was done.
當時有一篇很不錯的採訪
And it lined up all the top European captains who attended,
採訪裡列出了所有參加比賽的歐洲頂級隊長
and the topic was EHOME.
而標題叫EHOME
If you want to ever play good,
如果你想在比賽裡拿個好名次
you don't need to invite Chinese teams,
千萬別邀請中國隊伍參賽
because they are too strong.
因為他們實在太強了
So EHOME won…
然後EHOME贏了…
What do you think of the Chinese guys?
你對中國選手有什麼看法？
I never felt this outplayed in my entire life.
我這輩子都沒被打得這麼慘過
It's unbelievable how good they are.
他們的技術好得難以置信
Like, their timing, their discipline…
比如說  他們對時機的把握  他們的執行力…
They're really in control of the game, the whole game,
他們掌控了比賽  整場比賽
and they keep this control all the time.
而且他們能每場都保持這種掌控力
This is really crazy to see, actually.
這樣的場面真是太瘋狂了
It's because when we are at any international tournament,
是因為我們在任何國際賽場的時候
when all of the foreign team managers and team members see us,
所有的國外戰隊的經理和隊員看到我們的時候
everyone will all yell out, "EHOME!"
全體都會大聲地喊“EHOME”
EHOME! EHOME!
EHOME！EHOME！
Do you know how spectacular that is?
你知道那是一個多麼壯觀的場面嗎？
Actually, this is a story. It's a custom.
這是一個故事  是一個風俗
Which is when everyone sees EHOME,
當大家看到EHOME的時候
they naturally think the king is entering.
他們就自然而然的認為  王者要入場了
During this trip to The International, it's actually the same period as my exam periods.
其實這次國際邀請賽的時間安排跟我的考試時間是完全衝突的
So I treated it as a sacrifice that I've made for the team and for myself.
所以我這次放棄了考試  是為整個隊伍  也是為我自己
And I find that,
而且我發現
when it comes to pursuing your passions,
每當追求自己的摯愛時
it's really up to you to decide if it's worth the…
判斷是否值得做出這個犧牲…
worth the sacrifice.
完全取決於自己
When they're having exams, they don't allow him to leave the school.
當學校有考試的時候  校方是不會允許他離開學校的
So I told him really I said, "Mind yourself."
所以我讓他好自為之
Setting out on a career in gaming is risky. It's very risky.
職業電競選手這條路風險非常高
Because the examinations actually clash with the competition,
因為考試和比賽的時間總是衝突
and missing the exams without a proper explanation,
所以我總是無故缺席考試
the school didn't recognize the Dota competition as a valid reason.
校方才不會承認參加Dota比賽是正當理由
It's kind of breaking school rules.
這已經算是違反校規了
The school is very determined to stop him from pursuing his chance of going for this contest.
學校在阻止他參加比賽這件事情上態度十分堅決
So I think this has created a big stress for the family.
因此我覺得他給這個家庭帶來了很大的壓力
Gives his mother very headache, you know?
讓他媽媽非常頭疼
It's quite difficult for us to pull him out right now, I think.
但是我覺得  現在要把他拉出來很難了
You know he's so adamant about it.
他在這件事情上很堅決
So that's why when he told me he's going in August,
所以當他告訴我他八月要去參賽的時候
I said, "Then how about your school exams?"
我就問他  那你學校的考試怎麼辦？
"What are you going to do?"
你又打算怎麼辦
I think my mother, she was kind of at her limits,
我覺得我母親在她所說的遊戲拖累我這件事情上
telling me about how much gaming has been weighing me down.
已經說得夠多了
That was really the talk when I really opened my heart and I…
所以那次談話我完全敞開了心  我…
shared with her my passion for the game and how much I believed that,
向她傾訴了我對遊戲的激情
my team actually has the potential to win,
以及我堅信我的隊伍有機會奪冠
to be the best in the world.
成為世界第一
So we are stopping at nothing less than first.
所以我們不奪冠的話絕不會停下
This is how I tried to put it across to my mom.
這就是我試著讓我母親理解我的方式
By giving up so much to come here,
為了到這裡來我放棄了很多
I have absolute confidence in my team that we will win.
我絕對相信我的隊伍能夠奪冠
Alright the draft is under way.
現在正在挑選上場的英雄陣容
EHOME, they will select up their heroes.
EHOME將選擇他們使用的英雄
Scythe will start selecting theirs.
Scythe也會開始選自己用的
Looking now at both the teams,
現在看看兩支隊伍
it looks like EHOME they're fairly relaxed,
EHOME看起來很放鬆
while Scythe, you know they're eager.
而Scythe  我們都知道他們渴望勝利
They're all gathering around hyhy to pick.
他們都聚在hyhy周圍討論該選哪個英雄
If you have a losing draft, you will lose the game.
如果你的陣容就很差的話  你會輸掉比賽的
This is what I think of Dota.
這是我對Dota的看法
So it's really a lot on drafting.
所以陣容的選擇真的很重要
Drafting is where two captains will select what they want to play with.
陣容的選擇就是雙方隊長在比賽開始前選擇他們本場比賽想使用的英雄
What heroes are selected and what heroes are taken out.
可以選擇使用一些英雄  也可以禁止一些英雄被選
You can select five heroes out of a pool of over a hundred.
你可以從一百多個英雄中選擇五個
And can also remove four of those heroes.
同時禁用掉四個
So four heroes you think your opponent will want to use,
所以如果你覺得哪四個英雄你的對手可能會選擇
you can remove.
你可以把他們禁掉
Before any game, any match,
在任何一場比賽開始前
we will decide our bans and picks
我們都會針對我們的對手
according to which team we are fighting.
來選擇哪些英雄要禁用  哪些要上場
Usually we would come up with a very impromptu strategy,
通常情況下我們的戰術大多是即興想出來的
to try and fight their strat.
然後用以對抗對手的戰術
You really have to spend a lot of time thinking of the draft.
陣容的選擇非常需要時間進行思考
The draft actually decides a lot of the game itself.
選出來的陣容大多就會確定比賽的基調
EHOME, They're a team with so much experience.
EHOME是一支經驗十分豐富的隊伍
They already know the way they want to roll this one out.
他們已經想好了這場比賽的策略了
The only thing that's really going to make it or break it for them,
對他們來說唯一能夠影響比賽結果的
is if they can get their execution right.
就是他們自身的執行力
In that particular match-up,
面對那樣特殊的陣容搭配
we felt that we needed something that could instill the fear in them.
我們當時覺得應該選一個打亂他們陣腳的英雄
And Tiny looks to be the last pickup here from Scythe.
Scythe這邊的最後一個選擇是小小
A bit of an interesting pickup there by Scythe.
Scythe的這個選擇挺有趣的
It's going to start to change around their lanes completely now.
這樣他們的英雄分路就完全變了
With Tiny, it is good as a surprise strategy.
選擇小小是一個出乎對方意料的戰術
If another team doesn't realize where he fits into the whole lineup,
如果對手搞不清楚這個英雄在我們這套陣容裡的定位
then you can really throw the opposition off balance.
那你就成功的打亂了對手的陣腳了
He's moving away, but no, hyhy,
hyhy要往回走了  不對
he'll just turn around and just pops the Lina.
他要轉身扔起莉娜
I want to point out right now,
我現在想說明的是
that EHOME, they are not noobs.
EHOME並不是一幫菜鳥
This is just Scythe playing an amazing game.
只是Scythe發揮得太出色了
When you have such a huge audience and…
當有這麼多觀眾看著你
you know that everyone is at home watching the game…
你知道家裡的每個人都在看比賽…
they have their hopes pinned on you and…
他們把希望寄託在你身上…
I feel that…
我感到…
there's so much at stake.
這場比賽太關鍵了
And they should be able to clean it up right now.
他們現在要收拾殘局了
Tiny, he's gonna toss, he's gonna launch and he definitely gets the kill.
小小要使用投擲了  他起動了  他肯定會拿到這個人頭
We got 357 getting nailed out there.
357被秒了
Nature's Prophet going to get the last hit in as well.
先知A出了最後一下
It's the entire team down for EHOME.
整個EHOME都被打崩了
This is GG.
比賽結束了
This is now a double-rax, at least.
這至少要推掉兩座兵營
And EHOME, they're going to disconnect.
而EHOME  他們斷開了連接
We have our first Winner's Bracket Finalist.
我們第一支勝者組決賽隊伍已經出爐了
Scythe will advance.
Scythe將會繼續前進
EHOME will drop down into the Loser's Bracket,
EHOME則將落入敗者組
and Scythe will now finish up this game.
Scythe現在正終結比賽
Yeah, the one million is…
好吧  那100萬真是…
yeah, one million.
100萬啊
That's a lot.
真是太多了
It's going to make my time playing this game all worth it.
能夠贏下的話那我在這遊戲上花的時間就完全值得了
Didn't think smoking would do me any good.
從沒覺得抽菸對我有什麼好處
When did you start smoking?
你什麼時候開始抽菸的？
Two years back.
兩年前
都抽兩年了
Bad move.
不該抽的
That seems to coincide with when you and your ex-girlfriend broke up.
好像時間上和你前女友與你分手有點巧
On bad terms…
又不是什麼好事…
Seems like she's moved on already.
好像她已經放下了
Back then when she was playing the game,
當她還在玩這遊戲的時候
it felt like we had something we shared.
感覺我們共同分享著這個遊戲
Yeah, but right now, it's like…
不過現在  感覺…
I think she's following this event, but…
我想她還是在看這屆比賽  不過…
probably…
大概吧…
This event's big.
這是一次大型賽事
I hope I will get to make that phone call.
我希望我能夠撥出那個電話
Finally I'll have something I'm proud of to tell her about.
我終於能告訴她一件讓我自豪的事情了
Finally.
終於
When you played the Russians and the Ukrainians,
當你和俄羅斯以及烏克蘭選手比賽時
they were just the unpredictable teams.
你會發現他們捉摸不透
I had no idea what the Russians were thinking.
我完全不知道俄羅斯選手們的想法
That was their best weapon.
而這恰好是他們最強大的地方
Well, we're having fun.
我們玩得很開心
We're trying to relax.
也在努力的放鬆
We're trying to scare our opponents.
努力的讓對手害怕我們
Mind games. Mind games.
拼智商的遊戲  拼的就是智商
I turn off my brain in the way of being scared of someone.
我把我腦子裡負責害怕別人的功能關掉了
One of the things I really admire about him is how…
我最敬佩他的一點就是
he hasn't really had an easy life,
其實他過得並不好
but he's always so upbeat.
但他總是如此樂觀
He's always so cheerful.
他總是非常積極向上
When he first came on the Dota scene,
當他剛進入Dota圈的時候
he looked like a 12-year-old boy.
他看起來就像個12歲的小屁孩
Everyone was just, like, "Who is this kid?"
所有人的感覺都是  這個小孩是誰？
There's no way you can take this guy seriously.
你完全沒辦法嚴肅對待這傢伙
And then he would destroy you in games!
然後他在遊戲中就把你碾壓了
Как-то я видела, показали даже где-то в Интернете,
我在網路上看到過
как он работает с клавиатурой.
他在鍵盤上操作的手法
Это действительно завораживает.
我整個人都看呆了
Я думаю, что Данилу, может быть, и где-то пригодилась его игра на фортепиано,
我覺得丹尼爾練鋼琴對他這個有一定好處
потому что руки у него совершенно потрясающие.
因為他的雙手就像有魔力一般
He can make really good moves.
他能做出十分精彩的操作
His moves, I think are unique,
我覺得他的操作非常獨特
and they might win you the game.
而且這是能帶來勝利的操作
But he wants to rely completely on skill.
但是他想完全依靠技術取勝
He wants, like, an enemy against him,
他想的是  面對一名對手時
and he wants to kill him through skill, nothing more.
完全依賴自己紮實的技術擊殺對方
He wants to win the game.
他想贏得比賽
His disadvantage is that he doesn't have patience.
他的缺點就是缺乏耐心
He wants to make those moves.
他總想秀操作
He can get a little bit too silly in games.
有時打比賽他會表現的有點蠢
He will try new and different things.
他樂意去嘗試新的東西
He will overextend in team fights,
團戰時他有時會太上頭
because he believes he can get the kill.
因為他堅信他能殺掉對方
And his impatience can go too far,
而這種缺乏耐心有時會比較過分
and he might lose the game for us.
然後因為他我們輸掉了比賽
Oh, Nature's Prophet, he's going to go in.
先知要參戰了
This should be the First Blood.
一血應該要誕生了
They got the Sprout on Sansheng as well.
先知用發芽框住了Sansheng
There's probably going to be a double.
很有可能拿雙殺
Dendi's ulti, it hits!
Dendi的大招到了  命中了
Dendi, Dendi, no, no.
Dendi  Dendi  不會吧
He's not…he cannot be.
他不會…不可能吧
This is Dendi through and through.
那真是十足的Dendi招牌式操作
Starts with the Hex, goes to Cold Snap, he locks him in place!
先手羊刀  然後給上寒霜之足  敵人被控在了原地
Weaver really close to death!
螞蟻差點就被秒了
Manages to Timelapse back out again.
他想用大招恢復原來的狀態
Dendi will TP back to safety.
Dendi要T回家了
So GG being called by IG.
IG打出了GG
Na'Vi, they will take the game.
而Na'Vi  他們拿下了比賽
Our Winners Bracket Finalists are going to be Na'Vi versus Scythe.
我們的勝者組決賽的兩支隊伍將是Na'Vi和Scythe
Most teams that you see that have the most fan bases are full nationality.
大多數粉絲數量眾多的隊伍裡成員的國籍都是相同的
Our team is all spread out across the world.
而我們的隊員是來自世界各地
He does have it a little harder than us,
在這一點上他碰到的困難比我們多
because he doesn't really have this human support,
因為粉絲支持的確沒有達到這樣的程度
that we do.
比起我們差遠了
The hardest thing that I've had to really deal with in my life,
努力去說服我的家人同意我在電競這條路繼續走下去
is just trying to convince my family about my gaming career.
是我這輩子所做的事情中最艱難的事
It's really, really difficult especially when you start out slow,
真的非常困難  畢竟自己起步就非常晚
but you know there's a future for something,
但是你也知道  這條路是有未來的
and you put a lot of time into it,
而自己也投入了很多精力
and they keep telling you, "You should probably get a real job."
家人一直在說我應該找一份像樣的工作
I was born in the Los Angeles district in Lancaster, California.
我出生在加州蘭開斯特的洛杉磯區
I lived there with my dad and my mom.
我和我爸媽一起住
Around 2 years old, my dad left my mom.
2歲的時候爸爸就拋下了媽媽
He didn't really say anything. He just kind of…
他什麼話都沒留下  就是…
He just packed up and left.
帶上了他的東西離開了我們
She's had to raise us both while going to law school at the same time.
她只能獨自撫養我們哥倆  還要天天去法學院上課
It wasn't real easy as far as just got out of law school,
而且並不是念完法學院所有的課程這麼簡單
didn't have a job, had huge student loans to pay back.
當時還沒有工作  需要償還巨額的學生貸款
This job came up and so we moved here on our own.
找到這份工作後我們就搬到了這裡
So I've been raising them by myself ever since.
從那開始我就一人撫養他們長大
So this is a photo album that I made for Clinton.
這是我給柯林頓收集的相冊
As he was growing up, I put pictures in it as we went along.
我會經常把他成長過程中拍的照片放進來
My sons were both really active into sports and they wanted to do a lot.
兩個兒子都對體育運動非常熱衷  而且他們想玩的運動非常多
So I had to limit them.
所以我只能限制他們
They could choose two per season.
每個季節只能選報兩項運動
That was maximum for me being able to get them to practice and go watch their games.
只報兩項我才能抽出時間去學校看他們的比賽
That was tough.
的確是非常辛苦
And Clinton sitting on Santa's lap - his brother Santa.
這是柯林頓坐在他哥哥扮演的聖誕老人腿上
My brother's more angry at my father for leaving than I am.
對於父親的出走  哥哥比我更加生氣
He thinks about him.
他還念念不忘
He gets upset.
弄得自己非常難過
Compared to me, I just block him out and pretend he doesn't exist.
我就不一樣了  我心裡早就沒有他了  當他從沒存在過
Clinton already starting video games here.
柯林頓這個時候就已經開始玩遊戲了
He was sitting at his house, you know, playing Dota.
他在他的房子裡坐著  玩Dota
Doing it competitively, had a sponsored team and everything like that.
打打比賽  組個有贊助商的隊伍之類的事情
But I think that's when it started getting on his mom's nerves.
但我想也就是那時他的母親開始感到不安
I have a crazy sleeping schedule.
我的睡眠非常不規律
I'm on a European team so sometimes I have to stay up pretty ridiculous hours,
因為我是在一個歐洲戰隊裡  所以有時我得熬夜到很晚
or wake up at ridiculous hours.
或者很早就得起來
So the standard day for me is not so standard.
這樣我一天過下來很不正常
All the nights he'd be up and stuff, the dog would be up too with him,
他整晚都不睡覺  害得家裡的狗都要陪著他
and that would keep her awake most of the nights,
這樣一來她晚上也經常睡不著
and this is kind of where the tension got pretty high.
所以他倆的關係變得很緊張
You know, this went on for years,
你知道嗎  這種情況持續了好幾年
and it came to the point where I just told him,
到最後我就告訴他
I said, "You know what, you just need to go somewhere else."
“聽我說  你得搬到其他地方去住”
So I got kicked out of my house because of my gaming career, basically.
就這樣  因為我的電競生涯  我從家裡被趕了出來
When Clinton first moved in here,
柯林頓剛搬進來的時候
he was looking for a desk and there wasn't anything in the room.
他想要一張桌子  但是房間裡空空蕩蕩
And I had a lot of stuff we were getting ready to take to the dump.
當時我正好有很多東西準備扔掉
And Clinton went out there and he came back in with this green desk.
所以柯林頓去抬了這張綠桌子回來
And he goes, "This is perfect!"
然後他說  這下就完美了
So I didn't have a monitor, so I went to my friend,
那時我還沒有顯示器  於是我去找我的朋友
and he had a spare CRT monitor.
他有一台不用的CRT顯示器
So I got that, and then, obviously, I have two books here to hunch that up,
我就把它拿回來了  然後我又用了兩本書把它墊高
so I can actually see the monitor.
這樣我才能看得舒服點
So it's kind of a ghetto setup.
一切都很簡陋
Even when I go to competitions, I don't think I play any differently on the nice setups,
不過即便是跟在比賽現場用的高端設備相比
compared to this one.
這裡的打起來也差不多
Clinton's like the Rocky Balboa of Dota.
柯林頓就像是Dota界的洛奇·巴爾博亞
He's definitely one of the first big US players,
他毫無疑問是美國最老牌的選手之一
and honestly, I didn't even know he was that big.
說實話  我都不知道他已經打了這麼多年
In the North American scene, there weren't many good American players known back then.
在北美的Dota圈裡  當時優秀的本土選手非常少
Everybody respected Fear.
所有人對Fear都很尊敬
A lot of the people I knew, they quit the game.
我認識的許多人都離開了Dota這款遊戲
They moved on, stuff like that.
他們都去做其他的事情了
But I stuck with it so I ended up being like one of the oldest players.
但是我就認定Dota了  於是乎我就成了最老牌的選手
With all his years of experience,
他這麼多年來的遊戲經歷
and all his constant commitment to the game,
還有他對遊戲不變的承諾
he's really shown that he doesn't give up.
這都表明他不會放棄自己的職業生涯
Growing up without my father,
因為從小就沒有爸爸
I think in the end, not having someone there and teach me the guy side,
沒人教我怎麼做男子漢
and having a father to help you up,
也沒人教我為人處事
I think that it's actually probably made me the person I am today.
或許是因為這些我才形成了現在的性格
You know, I just make sure everything's running smoothly on the team.
你知道嗎  我要確保隊伍的所有事情都能順順利利
I kind of play, like, the father figure, I guess.
我猜我扮演的有點像父親這樣的角色
As a captain, I guess he felt he had that responsibility as well.
我想  他身為隊長也會覺得自己有這樣的責任
He was like pretty much my mentor.
他很像是我的導師
He did tell me one time,
他有次還特地跟我說
"Hey if you need someone to talk to," he would be here.
“如果你需要傾訴的對象  找我就行了”
So I kind of see him as a Dota brother.
所以我把他當成是Dota大哥
I've never had an ego thinking that I'm better than anyone else.
我從來沒覺得自己比其他人都厲害
I'm always there willing to help people who are new to the scene.
所以我非常樂意去幫助剛進入Dota圈的人
And that's always been kind of my role in the game,
天天幫助選手適應職業圈
by just helping players get up for the most part.
差不多已經是我的家常便飯了
Fear actually broke me into the scene, you know?
你知道嗎  事實上是Fear把我帶進職業圈的
It's very hard to get yourself out there.
要突破自己成為職業選手很難
I mean, back then, I was kind of like a fan boy of him.
以前我算是他的一個粉絲
You know, watching his games and what-not.
就比如總是看他的比賽之類的
And he gave me a shot to play at a high level.
然後他給了我一個參與高端競技的機會
I wouldn't be here today if it wasn't for Fear.
如果沒有Fear  我今天不可能站在這裡
I can guarantee you that.
毫無疑問
Going into the match, we were all thinking,
比賽開始之前  我們都在想
MUFC didn't do so well earlier, but…
MUFC之前戰績並不好  不過…
If we lost that game, we wouldn't win anything so…
如果我們輸掉了這場比賽  我們就拿不到獎金了  所以…
it was a high risk game.
這場比賽的風險很高
36 minutes in, almost a 7,000 gold advantage in favor of MUFC.
比賽進行到36分鐘  MUFC經濟領先了近7000
Toward the end of the game, we made a couple of mistakes,
在比賽接近尾聲時  我們犯了一些失誤
that put two heroes on the sideline for us.
導致我們的兩名英雄被擊殺
And they had all five still up and decided that they were going to go for our Throne.
而對面五人齊  並且準備直接推家
They're probably just going to push for the base.
他們可能會直接打基地
They're going GG!
他們要拿下比賽
They want to go for the GG!
他們想讓對方打出GG
No Fortification anymore!
沒有塔防了
We were really close to losing our Throne.
當時我們的基地差一點就沒了
It's below 20 percent HP.
基地血量已經不到20%了
And Online Kingdom, they are so close to getting eliminated from this tournament!
Online Kingdom就差一點就要被淘汰了
We just needed to do something.
我們當時必須做點什麼
Alright, I'm going to go on them! I'm going to initiate on them!
好了  我要幹他們了  我來打先手
So I ran in first and then they all went on me
於是我當時第一個衝了出去  吸引了所有人的火力
instead of focusing on the Throne, which is good.
他們沒有集火推基地了  很好
Again by Silvercross.
Silvercross又上來了
Fear, he's trying to retreat.
Fear在往後撤
He turns into a pig.
他被羊了
How the hell is he still alive?
他怎麼還活著
Go, go, go! Go, go!
上上上  幹他們
They push MUFC back!
他們打退了MUFC
We made this huge comeback where we killed all of their heroes.
我們打了對面一個團滅  實現了大翻盤
You know, started pushing.
開始我們的推進
Silvercross is down!
Silvercross被秒了
Morphling! He's out of this!
水人讀秒去了
The Top Rax will go!
上路兵營要沒了
There is no way now that MUFC can come back!
MUFC不可能翻盤了
But it will be Online Kingdom eliminating MUFC!
Online Kingdom將淘汰MUFC
What a incredible match…
真是不可思議…
Our whole team just went crazy.
我們整個隊伍都瘋了
Fear leading Online Kingdom to do the impossible.
Fear帶領Online Kingdom完成了不可能完成的翻盤
I've never seen anything like that.
我從來沒看過這樣的比賽
And stay tuned.
請不要離開
We'll be back here with more exciting gameplay coming up.
我們接下來還有更多精彩的比賽
Scythe, they are the 2008 ESWC winners.
Scythe是2008年ESWC的冠軍
One of the best Asian teams,
亞洲最頂尖的隊伍之一
but we aren't afraid of them.
不過我們不怕他們
We're gonna fight them.
我們將會和他們正面對決
I don't know about my teammates,
我不知道我的隊友們怎麼想
but I don't feel scared at all.
但我個人完全不怕和他們交手
I feel like I want to crush my enemy.
我想要碾壓我的對手
That's how I feel.
這就是我的感受
That's it.
就是這樣
Welcome to the Winners Bracket Final
歡迎來到勝者組決賽
where Scythe goes up against Na'Vi.
比賽將由Scythe對陣Na'Vi
The winner gets a slot in the Grand Final.
贏得勝利的一方將能獲得總決賽席位
The crowds were all cheering for them.
圍觀群眾都在為他們加油
And their draft was very scary.
他們的陣容選擇也很讓人畏懼
We were, like, caught off by surprise.
我和我的小伙伴們都嚇呆了
But, we were like, we've gotta win this, man.
但是我們當時仍然覺得  我們必須贏下比賽
We've gotta win this and show them who's boss.
我們必須獲勝  告訴他們誰才是老大
Scythe has managed to take all the best players from Singapore and put them in their lineup.
Scythe匯集了新加坡所有頂尖選手  然後把這些人組成了一支隊伍
One million!
100萬
Na'Vi, they look cool calm and collected.
Na'Vi看起來很從容鎮定
They know exactly what they gotta do.
他們很清楚該做什麼
It all comes down to gameplay right now.
現在歸根結底拼的就是實力
And I gotta say like, Na'Vi's lineup, it is not unbeatable.
我不得不說  Na'Vi的陣容並不是不可戰勝
Now they're gonna look for the initiation and possible kill.
現在他們要找機會先手並擊殺對方了
hy is gonna get caught.
hyhy要被抓了
Now bottom lane. Held in place.
現在看一下路
Sven stunned. No, Sven will go down.
斯溫被暈了  直接秒掉
And LighTofHeaveN, he helped out but Ancient Apparition gets the last hit.
LighTofHeaveN還在留人  但冰魂A出了最後一下
Na'Vi are dominating this final.
Na'Vi主宰了這場比賽
Now Na'Vi, they're gonna take the chance here.
現在Na'Vi要抓住他們的機會了
They're gonna go in for the GG.
他們要一擊制敵
And GG is the call from hy first.
hyhy第一個打出了GG
Na'Vi are already off their computers.
Na'Vi的隊員們已經離開了電腦
They're not even sticking around.
他們都懶得在對戰房逗留
They've got the GG.
他們拿下了比賽
Na'Vi are into the Grand Finals and will play for the one million dollars.
Na'Vi進入了總決賽  接下來將為100萬美金而拼
Scythe will go down. They will face the winner of the Loser's Bracket.
Scythe將落入敗者組  迎戰敗者組勝出的隊伍
We had just lost our confidence match against Na'Vi.
我們剛輸給Na'Vi一場本來很自信能贏的比賽
It was actually quite a blow to us.
對我們來說打擊很大
The game was really the turning point for me.
對我來說那場比賽是一個轉折點
Because I actually learned that in life you can only trust in yourself, actually…
因為我深刻的體會到  生活中你只能相信自己  還有…
not in the sense that you can't trust people.
不是說不能相信別人
But, yeah, like I said, the one who will never let you down is yourself.
但就像我說的  只有自己絕不會讓自己失望
Within the gaming world I'd like to be…be the first place.
在電競這個行業裡  我要做最頂尖的那批人…
You know, it's like I'm following behind my mother's footsteps basically.
你知道嗎  其實我基本是追隨了我母親的腳步
She worked really hard to get where she is,
她工作非常辛苦  才有了今天的成就
and I kind of want to be the same way.
我差不多也是這樣
I want to work hard for whatever I do.
我不管做什麼都想努力去做
For me, I mean I've never really had a dad.
對我來說  我從來沒真正有過一個父親
So if I had any questions about anything,
所以如果我對任何事情有疑問
the person I was most comfortable talking to was my mom.
我總是會願意和我母親說說
She definitely had the most influence on my life.
毫無疑問  她是我生命中對我影響最大的人
When she comes home from work,
當她下班回家時
she's always anxious to bring up the subject how she won a big case.
她總是迫不及待的提起她如何贏得一個大案子
And I'm always proud of her when she wins these big cases.
每次我都非常以她為榮
Because I know it means a lot to her.
因為我知道這對她來說意義重大
I mean, in the back of my head, I'm always, like…
我想  在我內心深處  我總是覺得
If I do well and if I win this tournament, you know…
如果我發揮出色並且贏得本次比賽
I'll finally be able to prove that I'm getting something out of this.
我也就終於能證明  自己從事這個行業並不是一事無成
And whoever wins this match will be facing up against EHOME.
贏得這場比賽的隊伍將面對EHOME
But whoever will lose it, is going to be eliminated already.
而輸了的隊伍將會被淘汰
Like, EHOME, they're looking really strong right now.
EHOME現在看起來非常強
We had the stronger late-game heroes, the better team fight.
我們有更強力的後期英雄  更好的團戰
Just all we had to do was just control the pushes.
我們所要做的就是抵擋住他們的推進
Online Kingdom, they're split!
Online Kingdom給了一個牛頭板
The stun on Santa! The splash as well.
板住了Santa  還有他的隊友
They're gonna claim a Windrunner.
他們要殺風行者
Will they? Yes they do!
能殺掉嗎  好的殺掉了
It's 2-0 for Online Kingdom.
Online Kingdom開局拿下兩個人頭
Moscow 5, not the start they wanted.
這並不是Moscow 5想要的開局
But Online Kingdom having an amazing start…
但是對Online Kingdom來說  這是一個夢幻般的開局…
We were so close to winning until some few mistakes that occurred in the late game.
我們幾乎都要贏下比賽了  結果後期出現了幾個失誤
They might go right now.
他們可能要上了
There's four heroes standing right next to each other.
是一個雙方4V4的團戰
The timing is wrong!
時機不對
There's communication problems because we're an international team.
由於我們是一支國際縱隊  所以交流出現了問題
So I think full-nationality teams have an advantage over most teams.
所以我認為真正意義上的國家隊相比其他大多隊伍都更有優勢
Almost there! Big try!
就快成功了  再加把勁
Fear's in trouble though.
但是Fear情況不太妙
He's shackled and Lacoste is in.
他被風行捆住了  Lacoste也來了
He casts his ulti as well.
把大招開出來了
And it just fell apart from there.
戰局從這裡就急轉直下
They just slowly beat us down.
他們慢慢的蠶食掉我們
Eventually they just broke our base and took every single one of our raxes.
最終他們摧毀了我們的基地  拆掉了每一座兵營
This is really hurting Online Kingdom.
這對Online Kingdom來說太傷了
They've lost three.
他們已經陣亡了三名英雄
And Enigma pops.
謎團拉大招
The team is wiped for Online Kingdom.
Online Kingdom被打了一波團滅
The base will be taken and Moscow 5 will now play EHOME and advance in the tournament.
基地被摧毀了  Moscow 5將會繼續前進  迎戰EHOME
Now, Online Kingdom, they are out. So much promise…
現在Online Kingdom出局了  之前的諾言…
It didn't happen in the end for Fear and the rest of Online Kingdom.
Fear和他的隊友們沒能最終沒能實現
And it will be Moscow 5 that will advance…
繼續前行的將是Moscow 5…
I think everybody on the team was very emotional.
我想隊伍中所有人情緒波動都很大
I could only imagine how he was feeling.
我沒辦法想像他現在的感覺
Some people take it more personally and they give everything to win.
有的人想的比較自我  認為自己為了贏付出了所有
It was very satisfying knowing that we reached that Top 8.
我們進入前八已經很滿足了
But he had better expectations for our team.
但是他對我們隊伍期望比較高
And we'd come a long way and it's all thanks to Fear.
我們能走到這麼遠都多虧了Fear
If you don't go as far as you thought you were going to be,
如果並沒有達到自己期望的目標
I guess you end up in tears or something.
我想總是會哭的吧
All of us are really disappointed, but…
我們都很失望  不過…
I guess that's just how it goes.
我覺得生活就是這樣
When I get back home, I need to make a big decision in my life.
當我回家以後  我得做一個很重要的決定
Like, just the benefits of playing Dota professionally, how much I can make from it.
比如完全成為職業Dota選手的好處  我能獲得什麼
And how much time I really need to put into it to be one hundred percent, so…
還需要花費多少時間才能做到100%投入  所以…
The only way I would ever do that is if I move in with my teammates.
我能全情投入的唯一方式就是和我的隊友搬到一起住
And have like a training house with them.
共同擁有一個訓練基地
So I know for sure that we're all dedicated.
我很肯定我們都非常投入和專注
I think things happen for a reason.
我認為任何事情都事出有因
And when things happen, you just do your best, and continue going forward with it.
當它們發生的時候  你只管做到最好  並且繼續堅持下去
I mean, deep down inside, I know this career is going to work out for me in the end.
我是說  在我內心深處  我知道電競職業生涯最後總是會讓我得到回報的
…who claim the championship
…冠軍的爭奪者
As for the Chinese teams I hope and know that they're capable of coming out of the Losers Bracket.
而我們中國戰隊呢  我也是非常地希望  也相信能從我們的敗者組殺回來
The top three teams are likely to be Na'Vi, Scythe, and a Chinese team.
目前來看的話  很可能前三強將會是Na'Vi  Scythe以及我們中國戰隊中的一支
Which I personally hope will be EHOME.
我個人是希望是EHOME
Emotionally, I would hope that EHOME would win…
感情上來說呢肯定是EHOME  我們中國自己的戰隊  又是一個老牌的戰隊…
Turning him into a pig!
羊到他了
They need to get this kill.
他們需要這個人頭
The stun! The Weaver Wave! It's a little piglet!
暈住了  螞蟻掛了蝗蟲  又一個羊
And it's dead! Slardar!
大魚死了
820, he's almost dead!
820差點就死了
Burrow Strike! Epicenter!
沙王穿刺搖大
357! It's a double-kill by the Weaver!
357幫螞蟻拿下雙殺
EHOME, they'll lose FCB as well.
EHOME打算賣掉FCB
Moscow 5, casualties of war.
Moscow 5送了波大的
Holy Hell.
我的天啊
In China, this game is a professional career.
在中國  這個遊戲已經是相當的職業化
We are stressed because we have to win.
他們有一個成績上的壓力
If we don't win or we lose to foreign teams,
中國戰隊如果不拿到成績的話  或者輸給國外隊的話
Chinese fans will have doubt in us…
國人會給他們質疑  也會造成很多…
Now Lion though is going to find him. Frog him up.
現在萊恩過來把他羊了
Finger's already started. There's the stun.
甩大然後給暈
Maelk in a lot of trouble.
Maelk麻煩大了
Really caught out of position.
被抓的位置也不好
AA ulti will fly in but hits on nothing.
冰魂大來了  但是沒中
Mania with the SK ultimate…
Mania的沙王還有大…
The situation is China against the world.
現在就是中國打世界的局面
If we win the championship, it is what we are supposed to do.
這本來就是我的本職工作  如果拿冠軍的話是應該的
I tell them, if you are coming here, you are here for the first place.
我告訴他們  如果你來這裡  就是來拿冠軍的
I will tell them every day.
我每天都會跟他們說
We must accomplish this. We must achieve this.
我們一定要做到這件事  我們必須要做到這件事
Now PLT. Support Teleporting in. FCB gets the first stun.
PLT在被追  隊友T過來了  先給了個暈
Misery over-commits on the top lane.
Misery在上路扛不住了
I can feel they really want to beat us, the foreign teams.
他們真的…我能感覺到  他們真的很想贏我們  國外的隊伍
PLT, he's had enough of this.
PLT已經受夠了
FCB! What a time for a Frog!
FCB  羊的時機真完美
Misery will pop!
Misery直接被秒了
But when they watch us play, they feel…
但是他們看我們打的比賽  他們就覺得...
that there is no way to beat us.
根本就贏不了我們
This is where my dad works.
這是我爸爸工作的地方
For as long as I remember,
從我記事以來
he's doing the logistics for the company here.
他就在這家公司做後勤了
So it involves the shipping of the containers from one place to another.
工作內容包括把一個貨櫃搬到另一個地方
When I was younger, he used to work, like, 15 to 16 hours a day.
我還小的時候  他一天要工作十五六個小時
He's pretty much given up on everything else in his life.
他基本放棄了生活中的一切
He's always made it clear to me that I should focus on my life, focus on my studies
他總是向我強調要專注於自己的生活和學習
so as to not follow in his footsteps.
這樣才不會走他的老路
He doesn't want me to be slogging as hard as he is right now.
他不想我以後像他現在這樣艱難
But the chance to be the best in the world at something…
不過獲得世界第一的機會…
you don't get it much in life.
這輩子都不會有幾次
I heard my son say
我聽我兒子說
he's working at this, what, Dota.
他的搞什麼Dota
He spends a lot of time and he gets nothing. For me, it's very disappointing.
他花了很多時間卻一無所獲  我對此非常失望
Never goes to school. He wants to play computer.
從來不去上學  只想著玩電腦
Then in the morning, sleep. Then computer until the next day morning. Then he sleeps.
然後早上睡覺  起來以後又玩電腦到第二天早上  然後又睡覺
The whole day at least 15 hours at the computer a day.
一天至少有15個小時都在電腦前
His life, my son's life is like that.
我兒子的生活就是那樣
For me, I hope for my son to study more.
我個人希望我的兒子能夠多學習一點知識
Don't like me. I never studied.
別跟我一樣  我都沒上過學
When I was young, I was also the same as Han Yong, always spent a lot of time to play.
我年輕的時候也和漢勇一樣  時間都用來玩了
But now I also regret, why I don't study.
不過現在我後悔了  為什麼當初沒有學習
But now I'm hoping my son continues to study to get an education better than me.
現在我希望我的兒子能繼續學業  別像我一樣沒什麼學歷
This is my hope.
他就是我的希望
I want to win this badly.
我非常想贏下這局
Are you ready for EHOME?
你準備好怎麼打敗EHOME了嗎
We'll do whatever we can.
我們會全力以赴
For hy, I feel it was a great choice - a brilliant choice.
對於hy來說  我覺得這是個很重大的選擇  而且非常明智
Because he was considering that we could have won.
因為他覺得我們可以贏
It's an opportunity that you shouldn't miss out.
這是個不該錯過的機會
So, get ready, sign in, log in, play around, test a little bit,
準備好入場  登錄遊戲  隨便打一盤測試一下
and then join the lobby in about 4 minutes.
然後4分鐘後加入房間
It's a once-in-a-lifetime chance.
這可是僅此一次的機會
If you miss it, it might be gone forever. You might not experience it again.
如果錯過了  那就永遠沒機會了  沒有機會讓你再來一次
And we have a rematch.
接下來還有一局
EHOME versus Scythe.
Scythe對陣EHOME
EHOME facing up against the team that forced them into the lower bracket.
EHOME的對手曾經將他們打入了敗者組
The psychological pressure is immense, especially upon the drafter.
心理壓力是相當大的  尤其是在選擇陣容階段
Because he is the one who is in the end responsible for the team's picks.
因為就是他最終負責戰隊的陣容選擇
No, no, no, no, no.
不行不行不行不行不行
Don't say no!
別說不行
No, no. Trust me. No.
不  相信我  別選
Wait, wait, wait.
等等  等一下
Tell me this. You really want it?
告訴我  你真的想贏嗎
I really think…
我真的認為…
It's the Antimage and SF.
要嘛敵法要嘛影魔
That's what I think.
我就是這麼想的
Shadow Fiend? Alrighty then. It's hyhy as SF.
影魔  好吧  是hyhy玩的影魔
Everyone knows how to counter a Shadow Fiend.
所有人都知道如何針對影魔
It's a very bold pickup here by Scythe.
Scythe這個選擇有點冒失
The fact, if Scythe wins the early game, they're going to gain so much momentum.
事實上  如果Scythe在比賽前期取得優勢的話  他們將士氣如虹
But if they don't, then EHOME will basically roll themselves into the Grand Final.
但如果他們做不到  那麼EHOME基本上就是躺著進總決賽了
hyhy, BKB is going to wear off pretty soon,
hyhy的BKB持續時間很快就會越用越短
Venomancer, great strike!
劇毒術士  漂亮的一擊
hy's dead!
hyhy死了
Stay in the trees now!
我叫你留在tree裡面喵
And he wants xy-, he catches up to him.
他還想殺xy-  他追上去了
And he brings him down.
成功拿下人頭
Hey! I told you to stay in the trees!
喂  我叫你留在樹裡面喵
Why'd you come out?
你出來幹什麼
Stay in the trees! I told you.
留在樹裡面  我都跟你講了
What an ulti! He Cogs!
發條精準一鉤  他用能量齒輪困住了對方
Chawy, he wants to leap, but there is just no Mana!
Chawy還想跳走  但是他沒藍了
I already told you.
我都跟你講了
I told you. Do you understand?
我都跟你講過了  你懂不懂
It's ok. Take it easy.
不要緊  慢慢來
If he can pop off an ulti like that, he doesn't have to reveal himself to his opponent.
如果他能在那放大的話  他其實沒必要暴露自己的位置
He can really just initiate.
他只要打先手就好了
Oh, there he goes! hyhy doesn't manage to pop off an ultimate.
他上了  hyhy沒能成功放出大招
Earthshaker is already dead.
牛頭已經死了
820, ruling gaming for hyhy.
820全程壓制hyhy
There are already three gone.
他們有三個英雄還在讀秒
Make that four.
現在有四個了
It's a double-kill for the Anti-mage.
敵法拿到雙殺
And they're headed for the tower right now.
他們衝著防禦塔去了
There is a GG—Good Game called by hyhy.
hyhy打出了GG
Scythe have had enough now.
Scythe到此為止了
EHOME will advance.
EHOME將會繼續前進
The Chinese hopes will stay alive.
中國Dota的希望還活著
As they will go up against Na'Vi with a one game disadvantage…
他們將面對有一個勝場優勢的Na'Vi…
The first-placing was very important to me.
贏得冠軍對我來說很重要
And to add on to that, my studies were also at the same time affected by everything.
而且  我的學業也受到了各方面因素的干擾
So everything was related.
所有事都是有關連的
When everything comes falling down at the same time, it's quite hard to handle.
當生活中的一切都崩塌的時候  生活就會變得很艱難
Things are all changed.
一切都變了
So you gotta plan your life again.
不得不重新計劃自己的生活
All over again.
從頭來過
I've learned a lot.
我學到了很多
You've gotta realize your flaws.
人都得認識到自己的缺陷
That's the toughest part, I feel.
我覺得這點是最難的吧
I don't do things as well alone.
我也不再獨自承擔一切了
So if you try to do everything by yourself,
如果一個人什麼事都想自己一個人做
it's not going to be possible, you know.
那根本不可能成功
I'm actually a believer of fate.
其實我相信命運
And I told myself that winning isn't necessary.
而且我告訴自己不是非得奪冠不可
Because there are so many more things in life.
因為生活中還有更多的東西
How you take care of the people you love.
比如你如何照顧好你愛的人
I think that's a very big thing. That's a very important thing.
我覺得這是件大事  非常重要
It's the most important thing ever.
是最重要的事情
Catch these guys.
抓住這幫人
It's not fair.
這不公平
Catch these guys.
抓住他們
I just woke up. It's not fair.
我剛醒  這不公平
My haircut…
我的髮型…
still…
還是…
crazy.
很亂
No?
不是嗎？
But I don't care.
不過我也無所謂
Ok, I have everything with me.
好了  我東西都帶全了
Let's go.
出發吧
We are now at the final day of The International Dota 2 Championships.
我們現在在Dota 2國際邀請賽總決賽日的比賽現場
It is Na'Vi, they have a one game advantage.
這是Na'Vi  他們有一場勝場優勢
Sitting very, very sweetly in the Grand Final.
開心地坐在總決賽的現場
Who will get a shot at the one million dollars?
百萬美金最終花落誰家
Na'Vi was running the same strategy the whole time.
Na'Vi從頭至尾都在使用同一個戰略
And no one seemed to be able to counter it.
但是目前為止還沒人能想出應對的招數
Na'Vi loves pushing from minute 10.
Na'Vi很喜歡從10分鐘開始就推進
And trying to end the game at minute 15.
爭取在15分鐘就終結比賽
Those strategies are very sensitive.
那些戰術容錯率很低
Because if you fail even once,
因為你一旦失誤
it can become a very difficult game for you.
整個比賽就很難打了
EHOME has been known for how well they defend their base.
EHOME以守高地著稱
So if there was a team that could stop Na'Vi's push it would be EHOME.
因此如果有一支隊伍能阻止Na'Vi的推進  那只能是EHOME
And let's get this game underway.
讓我們進入比賽吧
The players will start to pick up their heroes with one million dollars at stake.
選手們將開始選擇英雄  他們的選擇攸關百萬美金的歸屬
Na'Vi need to win two.
Na'Vi只需要贏兩場
EHOME need to win three.
而EHOME則需要贏三場
Running a very, very old school strategy with three core heroes.
選擇了一個非常經典的戰術  三核心陣容
EHOME managed to survive Na'Vi's onslaught early.
EHOME成功的抵擋住了Na'Vi前期的猛攻
It's all on Dendi.
全靠Dendi了
PLT TP's himself in.
PLT直接傳送過來了
Dendi on the retreat back out to the tower.
Dendi在往防禦塔方向撤退
Will he get himself away?
他能跑掉嗎
X!! Yes, there it is.
X!!  有了
Last hit, 357, the Venomancer brings down Dendi in the middle.
357的劇毒術士的最後一擊收掉了Dendi的人頭
Every time you see Dendi perform he's always playing very well.
每次你看Dendi在打  他打得都非常好
And he usually doesn't lose his lanes.
而且他對線一般都能占到上風
So, Dendi, his impatience is that…
所以Dendi的急性子比較要命
Chinese teams, they are patient.
中國戰隊的隊員就能打得很穩
They look out for the fact that you might cross a line.
他們就在找機會  就等你越過兵線
And they will take you and kill you and win the game through those situations.
然後就把你抓住殺掉  他們就是靠這樣不斷殺人贏下比賽的
Trouble in the mid lane again. There's already the Gush.
中路又有麻煩了  潮汐在後面吐口水
357, PLT, everyone is right on top of Dendi.
357  PLT  所有人都來殺Dendi了
He's in the wrong place.
他的走位出現了失誤
And the way Na'Vi played, they really gambled basically.
而且Na'Vi採用的打法  真的是賭上了自己的運氣
Dendi's really been ganked, just shut down.
Dendi的確被對面打了個措手不及  已經陣亡
And not a single kill to his name as well.
而且他現在還沒有拿到過人頭
Now Na'Vi going to assault inside the base
現在Na'Vi要攻進基地
Watch Artstyle. Tier 3 tower. VS Swap!
看Artstyle這一鉤  VS把屠夫換到高地塔下面了
Artstyle's in the wrong place!
Artstyle的走位出現了失誤
Doom there as well! BKB's both popping off!
末日給大  BKB時間也過了
Ravage will pop from LighTofHeaveN unable to affect EHOME.
LighTofHeaveN的潮汐準備踩大  但是對EHOME沒什麼用
Pudge will go down.
屠夫陣亡
They want to be initiated on.
他們要反擊了
Na'Vi, they need to fall back.
Na'Vi必須得撤退了
They take your little upsets.
只要你稍微走神
And just win the game through those mistakes.
他們就能馬上抓住機會擴大優勢  贏得比賽
GG from Na'Vi!
Na'Vi打出了GG
EHOME are celebrating right now inside the booth.
EHOME在隔音間裡慶祝自己的勝利
Na'Vi cannot believe it.
Na'Vi還不能相信
They've dominating this tournament until now when EHOME takes first match, so convincingly.
他們一直以來都是勢如破竹  但是第一場比賽被EHOME乾脆俐落地拿下了
That was the first loss of Na'Vi during the whole tournament.
這是本屆邀請賽Na'Vi首次輸掉比賽
They went undefeated until the Grand Final.
在總決賽之前他們是全勝的戰績
We're going to have a 15-minute break and be right back here soon.
接下來我們休息15分鐘  馬上回來
Na'Vi, they need to compose themselves.
Na'Vi需要讓自己冷靜下來
EHOME, well, they just need to be awesome…
EHOME嘛  他們只需要繼續保持這股氣勢…
What a play by them!
他們打得太精彩了
Any loss actually makes me pretty sad.
只要是輸了我就非常難受
We tried to put family pictures here.
原來我們會把全家的照片放在這裡
This is our mom and dad.
這是我爸和我媽
And I think that this one is our favorite actually.
我想這張是我們最喜歡的
My childhood, we lived a poor life.
小時候家裡沒什麼錢
And Dad was working for all our lives.
就爸爸一個人賺錢養活全家
But he helped us every time and every problem.
但是每次我們碰到問題他都會幫我們解決
I just ask him and he'll do everything for me, for Katya, for Danil as well.
我只要向他開口  他就會幫助我  卡佳或者丹尼爾
But Danil and Father were like friends.
不過丹尼爾和爸爸就像是對好朋友
Действительно мой муж был просто фанатичным рыбаком.
事實上我丈夫特別喜歡釣魚
Данил был, я бы сказала, можно сказать его самым лучшим учеником по рыбалке.
而丹尼爾  我可以說是他最好的學生
Данил имеет такое же терпение и такую же выдержку, как и его папа.
丹尼爾的耐心和忍耐力就跟他爸爸一樣
Он мог часами сидеть и смотреть на поплавок, который даже не пытался дёргаться.
他可以連坐一下午  光盯著浮標  人一動不動
They could sit with no speaking for hours.
他們可以一直坐著  兩個人一句話都不講
And just enjoy each other's company.
他們就是喜歡陪著彼此
They understood each other without words.
兩個人不用說話就能心領神會
One day I was going fishing.
有一天我出去釣魚
But dad never showed up.
但是爸爸卻沒過來
When I came home it was already super late.
我回家的時候已經非常晚了
He was feeling bad.
他非常不舒服
He went to the hospital. He decided to…
他去了醫院  他決定…
stay for a few weeks, you know, so we watch everything, stuff like this.
接下來幾個星期先住院  所以我們就天天看著他很痛苦
And…
後來…
cancer.
查出是癌症
It was a very big shock for me.
我當時真的是呆住了
Because he was very thin.
因為他變得非常瘦
I cannot understand that this is my father.
我想不明白我爸爸怎麼會變成這樣
We were all sure that it must be okay.
我們都認為他會沒事的
But it was a very short time.
但是病情只好轉了一會
I was really sad and was…
我真的非常難過
crying a lot.
大哭了幾場
I was upset about I couldn't say to him, many times, how much I loved him.
我一想到有好多次  我不能對他說我多麼地愛他  我心裡就覺得非常難受
Ну, после того, как папы не стало,
他父親去世後
он не ездил на рыбалку ни разу.
他再也沒去過釣魚
Ни разу.
一次也沒有
То есть…Пока это всё осталось в прошлом.
不過…現在這些都過去了
Actually I spent more time near the computer because I could not think about it.
實際上我在電腦上花費的時間更多  因為這樣我就不會想那件事了
It's like a distractor.
它能使你分心
It was like a start time, actually.
其實這就像是一開始的時候
The push to play more.
讓我去玩遊戲的動力
And that's maybe one of the reasons why I'm playing now.
這可能也是我現在成為職業選手的原因之一吧
Maybe I wouldn't play at all.
不然我可能根本不會碰遊戲
The relationship of Danil and my mom grew stronger these days.
這些日子來丹尼爾和我母親的關係更加緊密了
They support each other.
他們相互支持
And they are very good friends.
兩人已經成為很好的朋友
I think that this is very important for Danil.
我想這對丹尼爾很重要
You know, five years ago, I wouldn't care about many things.
你看  五年以前  我對很多事情都不在乎
Now, I'm thinking about it a lot.
而現在  我會去想很多
Something knocks you down, you need to learn to get up.
被擊倒以後  必須得學會站起來
So I'm trying to research this.
我現在正在努力學習
To learn to get up.
學習如何站起來
This is the most important moment in my life.
這是我生命中最重要的時刻
Because everything I worked on wasn't useful.
因為我所投身的事業並不是一無是處
And now I have a chance to win this tournament for my family.
而現在我有機會為我的家人贏下這個比賽
So we have currently EHOME and Na'Vi playing the Grand Finals.
現在正在進行的是EHOME和Na'Vi的總決賽
Na'Vi just lost one game versus EHOME, and it's 1-1.
剛才那一場Na'Vi輸給了EHOME  現在是1-1
So both teams have to win two matches in order to win the one million dollars.
所以雙方隊伍都需要再贏下兩場才能成為100萬美金的最終得主
Because our picks looked completely different, we were like passive and stuff.
由於我們的BP完全變形了  在戰術上變得被動
People thought we lost the first game, we're going to lose the second game.
大家認為我們輸了第一場  接下來這場我們還要輸
We were maybe a little bit demoralized.
我們的士氣也變得有點低落
We really needed to change to a different pick.
所以我們真的需要嘗試選擇不同的陣容
We were missing something.
我們的陣容還少了點東西
А Энигму мы взяли просто чтобы у нас был сильный тимфайт.
最後我們選擇了謎團  來增強自己的團戰能力
На замес пять на пять.
一場5V5的戰鬥
It was, like, the last hero left and I never played it before.
最後只能選這個英雄了  而且我以前還從沒玩過
Then, we're, like, "Dendi, you go!"
然後我們就說  Dendi  該你上了
And he's, like, "Guys, I've never played it!"
他當時就說  我從來沒玩過這英雄啊
"But, I can do it!"
“但我覺得我可以”
So we took the risk of taking him and risking maybe playing him badly.
於是我們冒著很大的風險  儘管可能用得不好  還是選擇了這個英雄
So it looks like down on that bottom lane, Dendi will be taking the Enigma.
看起來Dendi的謎團會走下路
It is going to be a very, very rough lane…
對線會非常非常難受
Na'Vi lost the game.
Na'Vi輸掉了遊戲
And they're playing something now that they're not as confident with.
現在他們採用的戰術自己也沒有太大自信
EHOME figured out Na'Vi. Figured out how to play against it.
EHOME摸透了Na'Vi  知道該怎麼對付他們
And I'm going to stick to my word and I'm going to say EHOME will win it.
我還是堅持自己的看法  EHOME會獲得冠軍
It was incredibly ballsy from Dendi to do that.
在他的隊伍就要獲得100萬美金時這麼做
On the verge of winning the million dollars for your team.
Dendi膽子可真大
That's very, very stupid.
這個行為真的是非常非常的愚蠢
That's suicidal.
等於是一個自殺式行為
Dendi really now caught out.
Dendi現在無計可施了
He's in trouble.
他遇到麻煩了
Rockets to fly in.
TK的導彈來了
FCB long way in on the tower, lands the stun.
FCB長途跋涉到塔前冰住了他
Tinker just lasers him to death.
TK一發雷射直接拿下
It will cost FCB his life.
FCB和他一換一
Then we made some little mistakes.
然後我們失誤了
We played a really semi type of, like, "turtle" strategy.
我們使用了“龜縮”戰術
Really passive. Really passive.
打得很被動  非常被動
We don't play like that.
我們平時都不那麼打
Puppey and Dendi just want to retreat back out.
Puppey和Dendi只想撤退
820! What a Fissure!
820  好板
PLT is there!
PLT也到位了
Echo Slam as well!
回音擊
Beautiful play there by EHOME.
EHOME這一仗打得漂亮
But I know if I die,
但是我知道如果我死了
I die not for nothing.
我並不是死得毫無意義
X!! in the middle lane…
X!!到了中路…
Force, Rocket, Laser.
推推  導彈  雷射
It's enough!
傷害夠了
Dendi goes down in the middle lane.
Dendi在中路被殺了
Sometimes it can be like, you dying but your teammates picking up more.
有時候局勢就是  你死了  但是你的隊友卻收穫頗豐
EHOME, they still want to push out that mid…
EHOME還是想推中路...
They weren't ready for Dendi Enigma.
他們沒有對Dendi的謎團做好防範
He was a patient Enigma, that was the most patient Enigma in the world.
謎團非常耐心  這是全世界最有耐心的謎團了
Dendi as well.
Dendi就位了
Going to look for the Hole.
準備施放黑洞了
BLACK HOLE!!!!
黑洞！
Three are going to go down for EHOME.
EHOME將陣亡三人
Currently, Na'Vi, they have the advantage now.
而現在Na'Vi占據了主動
That really impresses me how he's able to make that transition.
他的轉型真的讓我刮目相看
You just have to have the balls, basically.
這需要非常大的勇氣
He was scared of losing.
他很怕失敗
That's why he was so patient and he did everything right.
所以他非常耐心  步步為營
Their strategy is kind of similar to how EHOME won.
他們的戰術和EHOME之前獲勝的戰術有點相似之處
Na'Vi defeated them "Late Game".
Na'Vi通過打後期贏了他們
And I think this really shattered EHOME's confidence.
我認為他們徹底的粉碎了EHOME的信心
And GG is the call from EHOME.
EHOME打出了GG
Na'Vi, they take the game.
Na'Vi贏得了這場比賽的勝利
And they are only one win short of taking home one million dollars.
他們距離贏得100萬美金只有一步之遙
We hardly won the second game.
我們差點就輸掉第二場比賽了
Chinese teams generally are feared for their "Late Game" potential.
其他戰隊都很怕中國隊的後期翻盤能力
So we hit the point now.
我們來到了關鍵的一刻
The gloves come off.
現在該玩真的了
EHOME, they will master their knowledge, their experience, their calls up against Na'Vi.
EHOME他們將運用他們對遊戲的理解  經驗和執行力與Na'Vi一決高下
And Puck will be the last hero for Na'Vi.
帕克將是Na'Vi最後選擇上場的英雄
The nimble hero there already.
非常飄逸的一個英雄
Once again a lot of aggressive heroes for themselves.
他們又一次選擇了很多很強勢的英雄
Na'Vi LighTofHeaveN playing as the Beastmaster again
Na'Vi的LighTofHeaveN再次操刀獸王
with Dendi playing as the Puck this time.
而Dendi則使用帕克
If Na'Vi wins this,
如果Na'Vi贏下這局
they win the whole tournament.
他們就是整個邀請賽的冠軍
This Clash of the Titans right here
驚天大戰一觸即發
is something we will not want to miss.
相信在場各位都不想錯過
X!! will come in closer.
X!!就快趕到了
They will be able to get that kill.
他們能拿到這個人頭
Doom now on Dendi.
Dendi被DOOM了
Pulled in by X!!.
又被X!!拉住了
The entire EHOME team turns on him.
EHOME所有人都開始集火他
Lich will go down.
巫妖陣亡
FCB is on the run.
FCB在逃跑
XBOCT after the chase of him.
XBOCT正在追他
Might be enough. Needs some more damage.
應該能殺  但是需要更多傷害
Storm! X!! Long jump in.
藍貓來了  X!!遠距離飛了過來
Dendi Orbing up to the high ground.
Dendi往高坡放了個幻象法球
FCB! Puts on the Rift.
FCB趕緊開相位鞋跑路
Will he be able to get the kill? He's on the retreat.
Dendi能拿到這個人頭嗎  FCB已經撤退了
Yes, it is. Dendi with the last right click.
是的  拿到了  Dendi打出了最後一下
EHOME now, they're gonna rotate themselves down.
現在EHOME要被翻盤了
Na'Vi already in the pit.
Na'Vi已經在肉山坑裡了
They're trying to bring down Roshan - all 5.
他們五個人要打盾
Dendi! He's gonna jump out!
Dendi要跳出來了
He goes for the Dream Coil! He gets them!
夢境纏繞  大中了對面所有人
He gets EHOME! Holds them in the middle lane.
他控住了EHOME  所有人都被他困在了中路
Na'Vi already on their way out of the pit.
Na'Vi已經從裡面出來了
They're coming in to help out Dendi.
他們要趕來幫助Dendi
Then we just went in and demolished them.
然後我們過去把他們一一殺掉
Now they're on top of the Tier 3 tower.
現在他們已經到了高地塔
They're going to bring it down. Yes, it does go down.
馬上高地塔也要不保了  很好  已經攻破
EHOME, they're trying desperately to defend.
EHOME身處絕境還想防守
But Na'Vi, the onslaught will continue.
但是Na'Vi的屠殺還在繼續
The mid tower's already being pushed.
中路高地已經完全被破
The Tier 4 tower is going to go down.
雙子塔也要沒了
And running in right now is the rest of Na'Vi.
Na'Vi剩下來只要入場就行了
They are running forward to one million dollars.
他們已經向100萬美金奔去
And they will get it!
他們將是最終的得主
The GG is the call from EHOME.
EHOME打出了GG
Na'Vi have just won one million dollars.
Na'Vi贏得了100萬美金
EHOME do take home $250,000 in second place.
EHOME獲得亞軍  將帶著25萬美金回家
But Na'Vi are the champions!
而Na'Vi獲得了冠軍
There's moments of E-sports that are landmark,
這次Na'Vi科隆奪冠
and this is one of them. In Cologne.
將成為電競時代的眾多里程碑時刻之一
And Na'Vi, the winners.
Na'Vi  冠軍得主
You guys have just made history.
你們幾個剛剛創造了歷史
I was jumping on the sofa.
我直接從沙發上跳了起來
And screaming like a crazy girl.
一直在大叫  感覺像瘋了一樣
Because I was the happiest girl in the world.
因為我現在是全世界最幸福的
And my brother just won one million dollars!
我弟弟剛剛贏得了100萬美金
I think in 10 years time,
我想等過了10年
all the gamers which we currently have showing themselves,
那時候的這些選手們
they're going to be the guys we will look back at and say,
當我們看到他們  回顧歷史時
this was the beginning.
我們會說  這場勝利就是傳奇的開始
This is where it all started.
這是時代的揭幕
These are the guys that worked hard.
這些小伙子頂著風險
And they took the risk.
堅持不懈
They proved themselves.
他們證明了自己
And they forwarded the entire industry to the point where we could have a kick-start.
他們將整個行業推到了一個新時代的開端
We could show the world what we do.
我們可以讓全世界見識我們的能耐
And then who knows how big we could get at that point.
到那時候誰能知道我們能做到多大
We've come far already.
我們已經走得很遠了
When more and more people support it,
等到支持的人越來越多
and it becomes more and more normal,
遊戲也越來越普及
it's going to go from a niche to becoming accepted in societies.
電競就會從小眾項目變成被社會廣為接受的運動
I think in 15 years, E-sports will be bigger than football.
在我看來  15年後電子競技就會做得比足球還大
Than basketball. Than everything.
超越籃球  超越所有體育運動
That kid who you thought played too many video games,
你認為就知道打電子遊戲的小孩
is potentially going to be on a path, where he's earning $250,000 a year, salary.
將有潛力走上年薪高達25萬美金的一條路
He's flying the world.
他將飛遍全球
He's going to be endorsed.
他將有千萬粉絲
Gaming's the biggest entertainment industry in the world.
遊戲是世界上最大的娛樂行業
So if you're a star,
所以如果你是明星
you are potentially one of the biggest stars in the world.
那你以後會成為世界上最大牌的明星之一
So, if that, like everything else with computers grows exponentially or whatever,
所以  如果就像其他跟計算機相關的東西一樣以指數形式增長什麼的
then 5 or 10 years could be a big step actually.
那5年或者10年真的是很大的一步
Changing mindsets is never easy.
改變人們的認識可不簡單
So it's going to take awhile.
所以還需要一段時間
When the gamers now become parents,
等現在打遊戲的也有了孩子
we will be supportive of our kids playing,
那支持孩子去打遊戲的就不會只有少數
and I think that's really when everything will boom.
而且我認為那才是一切都開始爆發式增長的時候
After weeks of training,
經過幾週的訓練
a local man has led his online gaming team to the top,
他在線下將他的線上隊伍帶向了巔峰
placing seventh in an international gaming competition held in Germany.
在德國舉行的國際性電競賽事中取得了第七名
Yeah, she's definitely proud of me.
沒錯  她肯定會為我驕傲
I mean just, she had her camera out…
我的意思是  當她拿出她的相機時...
like, "Why are taking a photo of the television?"
她就想  為什麼要對著電視機拍照呢
I know she's really smart. She's a lawyer so…
我知道她非常聰明  她可是律師  所以…
But in the end, I think she'll be more understanding,
但是到了這時候  我覺得她會更加理解我
and be willing to support me more,
更加願意去支持我
so it worked out.
所以問題解決了
We were disappointed with our loss.
我們失利了以後非常難過
And, yeah, it's a mixture of both,
沒錯  更像是同時悲傷和喜悅
we're happy and sad that we got third.
畢竟我們拿到了季軍
Because of all the emotions, I felt like she was the one I wanted to share them with.
正是因為五味雜陳  我感覺我必須找她分享
And it got pretty clear only then that I had to get her back.
接下來很明顯  我必須要把她追回來
After the tournament I actually went back to look for her,
比賽結束了我真的回去找她了
and talk things out,
跟她把話講明白
and we have actually begun dating again.
現在我們又開始交往了
And things are actually going great.
兩個人之間變得越來越好
I love her, you know.
我真的愛她  就是這樣
She played a huge role, a very huge part,
她給現在的我…
in…
造成的影響…
in the me today.
真的非常大
One week ago it was 3,000 followers.
一個星期前有三千人關注我
I was happy.
我很高興
Then it's boomed. 8,000 followers.
然後就暴漲到了八千
It's not about the number.
我覺得這與數量無關
Even if it's one or two, I'm fine.
就算是一個還是兩個  我都無所謂
So you don't need to show numbers actually.
所以你真的沒必要去炫耀這數字
I think.
我是這麼想的
My father, I think…
我想  我父親…
didn't have time to understand what Dendi's doing.
已經沒機會去了解Dendi做的是什麼了
We lost him too early.
他離開得太早了
And if now he could see Dendi,
如果他現在能見到Dendi
I'm sure that he's proud of his son.
我肯定他會為這個兒子感到驕傲